Guide to the Marilyn Hacker Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marilyn Hacker Papers
1970-2001
YCAL MSS 753
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
21.2
(24 Boxes) + 1 broadside, 2 record album storage
Hacker, Marilyn, 1942-
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: May 2002 Acquisition, and January 2003 Acquisition.
Marilyn Hacker (1942-)
Marilyn Hacker, American poet and editor, was born in New York City in 1942 and attended New York University, receiving a B.A. in Romance Languages in 1964. Hacker's first collection of poems, Presentation Piece (New York: Viking Press, 1974), was the recipient of the National Book Award. Her other collections include Names (W. W. Norton, 2009), Desesperanto: Poems 1999-2002 (2005); First Cities: Collected Early Poems 1960-1979 (2003); and Squares and Courtyards (2000). In addition to writing poetry, Hacker was the editor of the Kenyon Review from 1990 to 1994, and has translated the work of many European poets into English.
Hacker was married to science fiction writer Samuel Delany from 1961 to 1974 and has one daughter. She lives in New York City and Paris.
Biographical information from www.poets.org.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, personal papers, photographs, audiovisual material, and printed material that document the life and work of American author, editor, critic, and translator Marilyn Hacker. Hacker's writings are documented by typescript drafts, proofs, and associated material, including correspondence with fellow authors and publishers. Kenyon Review materials document Hacker's tenure as editor of the journal, including controversy surrounding her dismissal. The Marilyn Hacker Papers are of interest for their documentation of twentieth-century American poetry and literary life generally, as well as the gay and lesbian liberation movements of the 1970s and after.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 18-22 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Marilyn Hacker on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2002-2003.
Kenyon Review; American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Editors -- United States -- 20th Century; Gay liberation movement -- United States; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographic prints -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Editors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; LGBTQ resource; Hacker, Marilyn, 1942-
- May 2002 Acquisition, 1970-2000; 20.2; (23 Boxes) + 1 broadside, 2 record album storage
  Arrangement
  Organized into five series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Personal Papers. IV. Photographs and Audiovisual Material. V. Printed Material.
  - Correspondence, Series I
    Organized under four headings: Alphabetical, Chronological, Kenyon Review, and Unsorted.
    - Alphabetical
      Scope and Contents
      Correspondence filed under this heading consists of incoming professional and personal correspondence from publishers, editors, academics, writers, artists, family and friends, documenting Hacker's activities as a writer, teacher, editor, and critic. Correspondents include Samuel R. Delany, Hayden Carruth, Tom Disch, and Joanna Russ.
      - "A" General (Box 1)
      - "B" General, 6
      - "C" General, 3
      - "D" General, 3
      - "E" General, 2
      - "F" General, 3 (Box 2)
      - "G" General
      - "H" General
      - "I-J" General
      - "K" General
      - "L" General, 3
      - "M" General, 4
      - "N-O" General, 2 (Box 3)
      - "P-Q" General, 2
      - "R" General, 9
      - "S" General, 6
      - "T" General
      - "U-V" General
      - "W" General
      - "W" General, 2 (Box 4)
    - Chronological
      - 1970-1974
      - 1971-1976
      - 1974
      - 1975
      - 1976, 2
      - 1977, 2
      - 1978, 2
      - 1977-1979
      - 1980
      - 1982
      - 1983
      - 1984-1985
      - 1986, 2
      - 1987, 4 (Box 5)
      - 1988, 2
      - 1989, 2
      - 1990, 2
      - 1991, 2
      - 1992, 2
      - 1993, 4
      - 1994, 6
      - 1995, 3
      - 1995, 3 (Box 6)
      - 1996, 6
      - 1997, 4
      - 1998, 4
      - 1999, 2
      - 2000, 3
    - Kenyon Review
      Material filed under this heading consists of correspondence and other papers related to Hacker's work at the Kenyon Review and Kenyon College.
      - Letters of congratulations, 1990-1991
      - Letters of outrage at Marilyn Hacker's dismissal, 1994
      - Letters of support for the Kenyon Review, 1993-1994; 2
      - Kenyon Review materials, 1991-1993; 2 (Box 7)
    - Unsorted
      - General, 2
      - Professional, 1970-2000; 10
  - Writings, Series II
    Organized under two headings: Writings of Marilyn Hacker; Writings of Others.
    - Writings of Marilyn Hacker, 1974-2003
      Writings consist of drafts (autograph manuscript and typescript, some corrected) of Hacker's poetry and essays (including translations), as well as notes and other related material. Unless otherwise noted, titles refer to poems or compilations of poems. Some files contain paste-ups, mechanicals, proofs and associated material.
      Largely arranged alphabetically by title or keyword; unsorted writings are filed at the end of the listing.
      - Assumptions, typescript, 1985; 12 (Box 8)
      - Going back to the river, typescript, 1990; 3
      - Love, death and the changing of the seasons, typescript, 1986-1987; 6
      - Paris writings, typescript, 1992 November; 3 (Box 9)
      - Presentation Piece, page proof (photocopy), 1974
      - Selected Poems, 1965-1990, 1994
        - Setting copy, 4
        - Paste-ups, 4
        - Page proofs, master pages, 2
        - Page proofs, corrected
        - Blue with corrections, 1994
        - Page proofs, corrected, 4
      - Separations, 1976
        - "Geographer," galley proof (photocopy), 1976
      - Squares and courtyards, 2000; 6 (Box 10)
        General
        Contains drafts, typescripts, mechanicals, page proofs
      - Taking notice, printed version
      - "The Trees win every time, reading Julia Randall," typescripts and printed version (photocopy), 3
      - Winter Numbers, 1994; 9
        Includes set copy, typescripts, paste-ups, and page proofs
      - Essays and poems, drafts, typescript, 6
      - Essays and poems, drafts, undated; 2 (Box 11)
      - Literary essays, drafts, typescript, 8
      - Literary reviews, 1980-1988; 6
      - Paris Material (translations), 1992; 2
      - Materials related to poetry in translation, 2000
      - Poetry translations, typescript, undated; 13
      - Poetry translations, typescript, 3 (Box 12)
      - Working Notebooks, undated; 10
      - Unsorted writings, drafts, 2003, undated; 6
    - Writings of Others, 1974-2001
      Arranged alphabetically by author. Works of unidentified authors are filed at the end of the subseries
      Writings of Others consist of manuscripts (largely typescripts) sent to Marilyn Hacker by authors. Some manuscripts include cover letters that provide evidence of Hacker's relationships with the authors, or the author's reason for sending the manuscript to Hacker for review.
      - Adorno, Pedro Lopez, 2000
      - Corvino, Peter, 2001
      - Delaney, Samuel, 1995
      - Dove, Rita, 1989
      - Ellingham, Lewis, 1987
      - Factor, Jenny, 1999
      - Finch, Annie (interview with Marilyn Hacker), 1994
      - Gregor, Arthur, undated
      - Jacobson, Josephine, undated
      - Kaddour, Hedi, undated
      - Khalvati, Mimi, 2001
      - Peacher, Georgiana, 2000
      - Ponsot, Marie, undated
      - Pritchard, Kenneth, 1996 (Box 13)
      - Rich, Adrienne, 1974
      - Riley, Dennis, 1987
      - Schulman, Grace, 1999
      - Searles, Susan, 1991
      - Selman, Robyn, 1989, undated; 4
      - Slavitt, David R., undated
      - Strickland, Stephanie, 1999
      - Unsorted Contributors, 1979-1980; 2
  - Personal Papers, Series III
    The series contains Marilyn Hacker's, medical, financial and publishing records, address and appointment books, and a scrapbook.
    - Address Books, undated; 2 (Box 14)
    - Biographical information, undated
    - Daily Appointment Books, 1981-2000; 16
    - Financial Records, 1988-1994; 2
    - Index Cards, undated; 6
    - Medical Records, 1992-1994; 2 (Box 15)
    - Postcards, 1974-1981; 7
    - Publishing records, 1988-1995
    - Scrapbook, undated
    - Unsorted Papers, 1975-1999; 3
  - Photographs and Audiovisual Material, Series IV
    Organized under five headings: Photographs; Reel-to-Reel Audiotapes; Sound Discs; Audio Cassettes; and Video Cassettes.
    - Photographs
      Photographs consist of prints, negatives, and slides, of Marilyn Hacker, and her family members, friends, and associates. Most of the photographs are informal snapshots, but several formal portraits of Hacker are included.
      - Photographs, 1975-1978; 17 (Box 16)
      - Photographs, 1979-1999; 34 (Box 17)
    - Audiotape Reels
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Poetry Discovery 1973, copy, 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002109975202)
        Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Marilyn Hacker, 1977 May 4; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002109975210)
    - Sound Discs
      - Joanna Russ, author of "The Female Man," interpreting her stories, Alternate World Recordings (Box 19 (Record Album Storage))
      - The Poetry and voice of Marilyn Hacker, Caedmon Recording (Box 20 (Record Album Storage))
    - Audiocassettes, 10; Also Included: an unwrapped, blank tape
      - BBC radio broadcast 'New Premises' presented by Nigel Andrews, with guest Marilyn Hacker, undated; 1 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002109975103)
      - "Cooper, Hacker Factor", 2000 January 26; 1 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002109975111)
      - "Letter-Joanna" (1 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002109975137)
      - "Letter-Joanna" (2 of 2 audiocassettes), undated; 1 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002109975129)
      - "Lost and Found," "I dream the Book," preliminary mixes, 1998 September 9; 1 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002109975145)
        A written postcard, included with this audiocassette, reads: M- These are the preliminary mixes, but I think they're 99% what we decided to keep on the master. You said you'd like to hear the "[Fovah]" poem with music. I hope you enjoy it! Love, M.
      - Lynda Hull, "Suite for Emily" and Best American Poetry Reading, undated; 1 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002109975152)
      - Marilyn Hacker, Modern Languages Auditorium - U of A, 2000 March 29; 1 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002109975160)
      - Aleida Rodriguez, Modern Languages Auditorium - U of A (2 of 2 audiocassettes), 2000 March 29; 1 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002109975186)
      - Marilyn Hacker, UCSD Special Collections, 1993 October 25; 1 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002109975178)
      - "Writers and Poets Program", Marilyn Hacker poetry reading, 1977 April 4; 1 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002109975194)
    - Video Recordings
      - Poetry readings by Maxine Chernoff, Marilyn Hacker, Greg Sarris and Melba Patrillo Beals at the SFSU Centennial Event at San Francisco Main Public Library., 1999 October 7; YCALMSS753_0001; 1; 01:35:50 (Box 22, Item barcode 39002102370047)
        "Poor picture quality due to the low light level at the venue."
      - Marilyn Hacker reads at Hudson Valley Writers Center, 1996 November 3; YCALMSS753_0002; 1; 02:03:13 (Box 22, Item barcode 39002102370054)
        "Also contains Sondra Audin Armer reading at Northern Westchester Center for the Arts, July 1, 1996, introduced by Cindy Beer-Fouhy and at Books and Things, October 25, 1996 with peer group."
  - Printed Material, Series V
    Includes clippings, pamphlets, brochures, printed material, photocopies of published writings by and about Marilyn Hacker
    - Clippings, 1985-1995; 11 (Box 23)
    - American Poetry Review, 1976-1996; 2
    - AWP Chronicle, 1994, 1996
    - Bananas, 1977
    - Boston Review, 1991
    - City, 4
    - Desire, 1981
    - La Quinzane, 1975
    - Margins no.23, 1975 August
    - The Nation, 1986-2000; 2
    - The New York Times Book Review, 1985 May 19
    - New York Native, 1981, 1986; 2
    - Say!, 1986 July/August
    - Times Literary Supplement, 1973
    - Women's Review of Books, 1985-1989; 2
    - The Village Voice Literary Supplement, 1989, 1990; 2
    - Posters and wrappers, 1976-1998
    - Unsorted printed material, 17 (Box 24)
  - Oversize Material
    - Medical X-Ray Films (Series III), 1992 (Box 25 (Oversize))
    - New York Times Book Review (Series V), 1980 October 12
    - Posters and wrappers (Series V), 1976-1998
    - Posters and wrappers (Series V) (Box 26 (Broadside))
- January 2003 Acquisition, 1974-2001; 1; (1 box)
  - Correspondence, 1999, 2000 (Box 27)
  - Sketch notebook, undated
  - "A tribute to Zenka Bartek," booklet, 1977
  - Printed Material, 1974-2001; 21